Guide to the North African Jewish Manuscript Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Morocco (general), Circa 1790-circa 1950; Series XI
  - Morocco
    - Letter to David Malul from Avraham Turgeman, 1952; MS.1825.1163; 1 leaf; 22 centimeters. (Box 23, Folder 50)
    - Homily for a person who passed away, Circa 1880-circa 1920; MS.1825.1181; 1 leaf; 16 centimeters. (Box 23, Folder 50)
    - Synagogue calendar of Torah weekly portions, Circa 1900-circa 1950; MS.1825.1182; 4 pages (2 blank); 19 centimeters. (Box 23, Folder 50)
    - Receipt for a purchase of meat, 1900s; MS.1825.1183; 2 pages; 15 x 5 centimeters. (Box 23, Folder 51)
    - Two letters, Circa 1900-circa 1950; MS.1825.1185; 2 pages; 21 centimeters. (Box 23, Folder 51)
      Place: Unknown. One letter is written in blue ink in Hebrew. Second letter, written in red ink in Judeo-arabic, sent by a father to his son.
    - Pages from a larger manuscript including homilies for people who passed away, Circa 1890-circa 1910; MS.1825.1186.1-.4; 14 pages (I blank); 21 centimeters. (Box 23, Folder 52)
      Place: Unknown. The homilies were delivered in accordance with suitable weekly Torah portions.
    - Halakhic decision concerning partnership, Circa 1880-circa 1900; MS.1825.1188; 2 pages; 21 centimeters. (Box 23, Folder 53)
      Place: Unknown. On the back of the document there are three letters with regard to purchase of wheat. In addition there is a paragraph with instructions for making an amulet.
    - Page from a larger collection of homilies, Circa 1890-circa 1910; MS.1825.1189; 2 pages; 19 centimeters. (Box 23, Folder 53)
    - Two homilies, Circa 1850-circa 1900; MS.1825.1190; 2 pages; 27 centimeters. (Box 23, Folder 53)
      Place: Unknown. One homily is about King David and the other is about punishment given to a man in Gehenna for sins he committed on earth.
    - Homily containing words of praise for prayer shawls and phylacteries, Circa 1890-circa 1910; MS.1825.1191; 1 leaf; 12 x 19 centimeters. (Box 23, Folder 54)
    - Homily delivered in the presence of great sages by a young rabbi, Circa 1850-circa 1900; MS.1825.1193; 2 leaves; 12 x 18 centimeters. (Box 23, Folder 54)
    - Document regarding a business partnership, 1847; MS.1825.1369; 4 pages (2 blank); 23 centimeters. Fragile with some loss of text. Pages are glued together. (Box 23, Folder 54)
      Place: Fès or Sefrou. All the names mentioned in the document (Elbaz, Oliel, Shitrit) point to Morocco. Among the signatories is Rahamim Yosef.
  - Folk religion
    - Collection of folk remedies, Circa 1840-circa 1860; MS.1825.0064; 48 pages; 21 centimeters. (Box 24, Folder 1)
      Place: Meknès?. Notebook with more than 100 medical and magical treatments. Some of the recipes include ingredients such as serpent's venom, onion, garlic, etc. The manuscript lacks any indication of the writer's identity or location, although it may come from Meknès.
    - Recipe for a folk remedy, Circa 1840-circa 1860; MS.1825.0065; 1 leaf; 15 centimeters. (Box 24, Folder 2)
      Place: Unknown. Manuscript similar to MS.1825.0064 and could be a page from a longer document. The recipe calls for mixing goatskin with whitewash, dust, etc. The document lacks any indication of the writer's identity or location.
    - Calculations to predict solar eclipse, Circa 1840-circa 1860; MS.1825.0071; 2 pages; 30 centimeters. (Box 24, Folder 2)
      Place: Unknown. A calendar calculation by an anonymous rabbi attempting to predict whether a solar eclipse would take place during the month of Elul 5637 (1877). The document ends before he reached a conclusion.
    - Page from a book of folk-remedies and amulets, Circa 1880-circa 1900; MS.1825.0247; 4 pages; 21 centimeters. Ink stains. Text in blue and black ink. (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Fragment of Shulhan Arukh ha-Ari, attributed to Isaac Luria, Circa 1900-circa 1920; MS.1825.0345; 4 pages (3 blank); 16 centimeters. (Box 24, Folder 3)
      Place: Morocco. Kabbalistic text relating to repentance from sin. One of the rabbis quoted here is David Maghar. This text is parallel to Shulhan Arukh shel Rabenu Yitshak Lurya, Vilna 1881, pages 22b-23a.
    - Fragment of Nehar Shalom by Shalom Sharabi, Circa 1880-circa 1900; MS.1825.1029; 2 pages; 20 centimeters. Torn with loss of text. (Box 24, Folder 4)
      Place: Morocco. This text is parallel to ʻEts Ḥayim - Nehar Shalom, Jerusalem 1910, pages 35a-35b.
    - Fragment of Passover Haggadah with a kabbalistic commentary, 1800s; MS.1825.1031; Two small fragments. (Box 24, Folder 4)
      Place: Morocco. Very likely to be a copy from a Haggadah with a kabbalistic commentary dealing with asceticism. This document was copied in the nineteenth century.
    - Fragments, 1800s; MS.1825.1032; 2 pages; 21 centimeters. Page is mostly blank, with small fragments. (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Kabbalistic compositions, Circa 1930-circa 1940?; MS.1825.1033; 268 pages; 23 centimeters. (Box 24, Folder 5)
      Place: Unknown. The manuscript begins with the composition Goral ha-Ḥol attributed to Abraham ben Meïr Ibn Ezra, accompanied by the Moroccan Judeo-Arabic commentary of an anonymous author focusing on astrological fates (goralot). The commentary includes late kabbalistic ideas protruding into the original text, such as those of Moses ben Jacob Cordovero (1522-1570) of Tsefat and Joseph Montefiore (eighteenth century) of Livorno [see page 115b]. The second composition, Sidra de-Goralot, is a Moroccan Judeo-Arabic astrological composition on fates and the zodiac signs. The pagination of the volume is backwards, with printed page numbers in the order of a European language. The commentary on Goral ha-Ḥol is on pages 141a-104b and Sidra de-Goralot is on pages 101a-15a.
    - Copy of Sefer She'erit Yosef and other texts, Undated; MS.1825.1034; 123 pages; 23 centimeters. Partly paginated. (Box 24, Folder 6)
      Place: Unknown. The manuscripts were copied from Sefer She'erit Yosef, which was printed together with Sefer Re'ashim u-re'amim and Sefer Orhot Hayim in the Thessalonikē edition of 1568. The first text, on pages 1a-59a, contains Sheʼerit Yosef, a treatise on calculations of the Hebrew calendar written in a rhymed poem by Joseph ben Shem-Tob ben Jeshuah Chay with commentary by Daniel ha-Kohen. On pages 59a-b is Seder Re'ashim u-Re'amim (signs of earthquakes and thunders) by Judah ben Joseph Alcorsono of Taza, Morocco, fourteenth century. The third text, on pages 60a-62a, is a portion of the anonymous Sefer Orḥot Ḥayim attributed to R. Eliezer ha-Gadol. Compare: MS New York JTS 2570, MS New York JTS Benaim 58, MS Tel Aviv Gross 308.
    - Page from a talmudic composition, Circa 1850-circa 1900; MS.1825.1035; 2 pages; 18 centimeters. (Box 24, Folder 7)
      Place: Morocco. Includes copies from Babylonian Talmud tractates Yevamot, Nimuḳe Yosef, and Bet Shemu'el.
    - Collection of talismans, cures and writings relating to magic and astrology, 1934; MS.1825.1054; 226 pages (3 blank); 23 centimeters. (Box 24, Folder 8)
      Place: Morocco. Manuscript written and illustrated by Mordekhai Amar. On the ornamented title page, he writes that the volume contains "cures and protections that I copied from earlier books... talismans, cures, and lots." The texts are written in Hebrew, Aramaic, and Arabic (both in Arabic letters and in Hebrew letters). The volume includes: Petikhat Eliyahu, a Zoharic portion found in the liturgy; Hebrew and Arabic amulets and folk recipes for protecting one's house, erotic magic, fertility, and other remedies; an alphabetical list of medicaments to be used in preparing amulets; a table of drugs and matters divided in accordance with the seven astronomical bodies and the seven days; selected texts from the Qur?an written in Hebrew letters, including twelve Suras with drawings of corresponding signs of the Zodiac; pseudo-Latin formulas to fend off demons.
- Palestine, Europe, Americas, Eygpt, 1714-1962; Series XII
  Series XII documents from other parts of the world that relate to North African Jewry. The documents in Box 25, folders 1-16 are mainly from the Maghrebi community in Palestine. Some consist of letters seeking support for institutions in the Holy Land from North African communities and some concern people or property in Morocco. Box 25, folders 17-23 contain documents from Europe, North and South America, and Egypt. They consist of letters to North African rabbinic authorities, and documents concerning Maghrebi emigrants and their correspondence with relatives they left behind. Oversize documents from this series are in Box 35.
  - Palestine
    - Collection of four documents concerning a rabbinic emissary sent from the Maghrebi community of Jerusalem to Morocco, 1934; MS.1825.0019; 7 leaves; 33 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 1)
      Place: Jerusalem. Collection of four documents: 1. Manuscript from the Maghrebi community of Jerusalem, nominating ʻAmram Aburabiʻa in 1934 as emissary to Morocco. 2. Details of the fundraising mission. The importance of this text derives from the long and detailed list of almost one hundred communities in Morocco. Signatories to the nomination include the famous Yitsḥaḳ ʻAmram Sabbah, Shalom Azulai, Mordekhai Azran, Saʻid ha-Kohen, Yosef Shelush, and Avraham ben Mazliaḥ. 3. & 4. Two documents authorizing a substitute emissary. Since ʻAmram Aburabiʻa became very sick in Morocco, he nominated Shelomoh ha-Kohen Sḳali to replace him. To lend authority to the re-nomination, Aburabiʻa was joined by three members of the rabbinic court of Casablanca.
    - Rabbinic emissary documents, 1800s; MS.1825.0020.01-.33; 33 leaves; 10-29 centimeters. Each leaf is in a separate sleeve in an archival binder. (Box 25, Folder 2-6)
      Place: Tiberias. Thirty three documents, almost all of which were written in or sent to Tiberias. They date from the beginning of the nineteenth century. Many of these documents were sent to Shelomoh Abiṭbol and his son Amor Abiṭbol in the community of Sefrou. The others were sent to different communities in North Africa. Only a few of these documents are included in Sheluhe Erets Yisrael by Abraham Yaari. A very important subject in most of the letters is the wish of leaders in Jerusalem for a portion of the money collected by Tiberias; however, all of the authorities mentioned in the documents refused to accept this, and the money was sent to Tiberias. One of the most interesting documents (MS.1825.0020.21) was sent by sages of Constantine and other communities in Algeria to Tiberias, declaring that they sent the money specifically to Tiberias and not to Jerusalem. MS.1825.0020.27, signed by the leading authorities of the community of Fès, echoes the position of Constantine. Another important subject in this document is the percentage kept by the emissaries for themselves. MS.1825.0020.10 is not a rabbinic emissary document, but rather a rabbinic decision concerning a dispute in Tiberias in 1843 signed by three rabbis, including Naḥum Mizraḥi.
    - Document written by the judges of the Maghrebi community of Jerusalem assigning a messenger to deliver a bill of divorce, 1920; MS.1825.0228; 1 leaf; 27 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 7)
      Place: Jerusalem. The document is signed by Shimon Ashriki, Eliyahu Lajimi and Yaakov ben Attar.
    - Demand of the leaders of the Maghrebi community in Jerusalem for funds that were collected for them by Shelomoh Ha-Kohen Skali in Casablanca, 1938; MS.1825.0431; 1 leaf; 28 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 7)
      Place: Jerusalem. Typewritten. Signed by Avraham Almalih, the head of the Maghrebi community in Jerusalem.
    - Letter from Eliezer Monsour Settehon of Tiberias to Yeudah Ben Shimol in Tangier, 1917; MS.1825.0457; 1 leaf; 27 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 7)
      Place: Tiberias.
    - Request by the rabbi and emissary Eliyahu Illoz to the rabbis of Tangier to assist Refael Bibas with debts that he took upon himself in order to build a Talmud Torah, 1927; MS.1825.0460; 1 leaf; 28 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - Letter from Yaakov Hai Berdugo of Tiberias to Yemin Ha-Kohen in Tangier requesting him to meet his boat when he arrives in Tangier, 1933; MS.1825.0468; 1 leaf; 28 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - Letter by Shelomoh ha-Kohen Skali Zaguri from Jerusalem to Refael Barukh Toldedano and Yosef Mesas of Meknès, 1930; MS.1825.0477; 1 leaf; 13 x 21 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - Letter from Yaakov Berdugo in Tiberias to Yemin ha-Kohen of Tangier relating to financial matters, 1931; MS.1825.0488; 1 leaf; 27 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - Document appointing an emissary to expel a woman from Fès, 1909; MS.1825.0494; 1 leaf; 29 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 9)
      Place: Jerusalem. The emissary subsequently appointed a different emissary in Morocco tp perform the duty. Signed by three rabbis in Jerusalem, including Yitshak Labaton.
    - Responsum letter to Shelomoh Berdugo in Meknès from Eliezer Berdugo in Jerusalem, 1905; MS.1825.0532; 4 pages (3 blank); 21 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 9)
      Place: Jerusalem. Written in Judeo-Arabic.
    - Letter fom Yaakov Berdugo giving power of attorney to Shelomoh Berdugo, 1905; MS.1825.0533; 4 pages (2 blank); 21 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - Letter from Jerusalem regarding the study of Torah in Palestine, 1874; MS.1825.0718; 2 pages; 17 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 10)
      Place: Jerusalem. The letter was written by Yisrael Mitrani, who recounts that he was born in "Kirkisiya," probably Kırkışık, Turkey.
    - Legal decision concerning property in Fès, 1885; MS.1825.0723; 4 pages; 29 centimeters. (Box 35, Folder 5)
      Place: Jerusalem, Fès. Document includes signatures and stamp of the Maghrebi rabbinical court in Jerusalem.
    - Letter from the Jewish community in Palestine to the Jews of Morocco requesting assistance for orphanages, 1880; MS.1825.0724; 4 pages; 23 centimeters. (Box 35, Folder 5)
      Place: Palestine. The letter stresses the importance of charity to orphanages in the land of Israel.
    - Letter, Circa 1880-circa 1900; MS.1825.0732; 1 leaf; 21 centimeters. Brittle, torn with loss of text. (Box 25, Folder 10)
      Place: Palestine?.
    - Letter of thanks from the land of Israel to a rabbi in North Africa, Circa 1880-circa 1900; MS.1825.0733; 4 pages (1 blank); 22 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 10)
      Place: Palestine. Letter of thanks from the land of Israel to a rabbi in North Africa who had collected and sent money for the poor.
    - Letter from Tiberias to Amsterdam requesting charity, 1882; MS.1825.0738; 1 page; 17 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 11)
      Place: Tiberias. The letter was writtten by Yitshak ben Tsiyon ha-Levi.
    - Letter from Tiberias requesting aid from Gibraltar, 1902; MS.1825.0740; 1 leaf; 27 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 11)
      Place: Tiberias. Letter from Shelomoh Rahamim Abulafia in Tiberias to Mosheh Ben Naim in Gibraltar.
    - Letter concerning funds, 1909?; MS.1825.0742; 4 pages (2 blank); 27 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 12)
      Place: Tiberias. A letter of complaint from the rabbis in Tiberias to Refael Hayim Mosheh Ben Naim that they have not received funds that were sent to them.
    - Letter in Ladino to Yitshak Bakhar from Avraham Philosoph, 1919; MS.1825.0753; 1 leaf; 22 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 12)
      Place: Jerusalem or Balkans?. The letter was probably from Jerusalem or the Balkans.
    - Rabbinic emissary document from Jerusalem to various cities in Morocco, 1926; MS.1825.0762; 20 pages (15 blank); 24 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 13)
      Place: Jerusalem. The official stamps of the rabbis as well as their signatures appear in several places in the document.
    - Responsum from Jerusalem to Yemen concerning bill of divorce, 1900; MS.1825.0769.1-.4; 4 leaves; 27 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 14)
      Place: Jerusalem. Responsum from the President of the Bet-Din Sepharadi in Jerusalem to the community in Yemen. Typewritten and mimeographed. Letterhead of Abraham Pelosoph. Rabbinic response to a question with regard to a divorce document from a community in Yemem (Altsla'?).
    - Collection of sermons of rabbis from the Abulafia family from Tiberias, 1800s; MS.1825.1064; 390 pages; 20 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 15)
      Place: Tiberias. The Abulafia family was part of the community that came from North Africa and settled in Tiberias. This collection of sermons was carried from Tiberias to Corsica to Morocco to Tangier. It was acquired in 2010 from the collection of Yaakov Dahan. Original tooled leather binding with the title Sefer derushim on the spine and the name Shelomoh Abulʻafia on the front cover. According to the scholar Moshe Bar-Asher, this manuscript is unknown and important.
    - Letter sent by Shimon Shabatai in Tsefat to Avraham Sabbah in Rabat, 1931; MS.1825.1157; 1 leaf; 25 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 16)
      Place: Tsefat. An alternate address in Tel Aviv is also included.
    - Two letters written by Altar Mazuz from Djerba to Asher Haddad, 1962; MS.1825.1167; 4 pages; 15 centimeters., 21 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 16)
      Place: Israel. The letter was written in Israel. In the back of both documents somebody added different lists at a later period, perhaps the 1970's.
  - Europe, Americas, Egypt
    - Poems for the circumcision ceremony (Pizmonim le-milah u-virkhoteha), 1845; MS.1825.0003; 40 pages; 17 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 17)
      Place: Terceira. Written by Maimon Abouhbout for Mosheh Sabbah, both members of the Moroccan community in Terceira. There is an opening text praising Mr. Sabbah and his wife in the first two pages of the manuscript.
    - Question concerning laws of ritual immersion pertaining to refugees, 1940; MS.1825.0436.1; 2 pages; 27 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 18)
      Place: France. Letter from Menahem Coriat in France to Rabbi Elyakim in Casablanca asking about observant Jews who are Holocaust refugees from Poland and immersion that is not in a mikvah, but rather in a bathtub or a shower.
    - Question regarding laws of immersion in a ritual bath (mikvah) pertaining to refugees, Circa 1940-circa 1942; MS.1825.0436.2; 12 pages; 21 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 18)
      Place: Europe. Letter sent from Europe to Rabbi Elyakim in Casablanca.
    - Letter from Rabbi M. Kramer of Vienna to the rabbis of Tangier requesting support for refugees of World War I in the land of Israel, 1920; MS.1825.0462; 1 leaf; 27 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 19)
      Place: Vienna. Also signed by Laser S. Averbach.
    - Letter from the rabbi Meir Yehudah Brunschwig to the rabbis of Tangier with regard to Jewish dietary law and the need to validate all certificates of kashrut, 1924; MS.1825.0480; 1 leaf; 28 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 19)
      Place: Strasbourg. From the Kehilat Mahzike ha-dat in Strasbourg.
    - Letter in Judeo-Arabic from Avraham Yitshak Azulai, 1913 or 1914; MS.1825.0513; 2 pages; 27 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 19)
      Place: Coary, Brazil. The name is printed on the stationery as Abraham Isaac Azulay.
    - Novellae and laws concerning Passover, Circa 1840-circa 1860; MS.1825.0720; 6 pages; 33 centimeters. Damaged fragment with missing text (Box 25, Folder 20)
      Place: Italy?. Halakhic text concerning laws of leaven on Passover written by a Sephardic sage and emissary from the Maghrebi community of Tiberias, Yaakov [Rahamim?] Shealtiel Ninyo. The handwriting is Maghrebi. Ninyo traveled to Turkey and Italy. The document was probably written in Italy, but the name of the locality is hard to decipher.
    - Letter written by a man, who traveled from Morocco to New York, to his family still in Morocco, 1920; MS.1825.0735.1-.3; 12 pages (4 blank); 22 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 21)
      Place: New York. The letter describes the wonders of America and also gives a description of the Sephardic Jews there.
    - Sḳizze der geshikhṭe der yuden in der Barbaryah, 1808; MS.1825.1052; 118 pages; 21 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 22)
      Place: Paris. Manuscript in Yiddish, "A Sketch of the History of the Jews in Barbary," written by Meir Fischels. Although the author calls this manuscript "part one" of his history, no other volume is known and the work was never printed. From the collection of Chimen Abramsky, purchased from Sotheby's on the Rosalyn and Joseph Newman Collection Fund, 2011.
    - Letter concerning mourning a deceased rabbi, 1908; MS.1825.1226; 1 leaf; 21 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 23)
      Place: Alexandria. The letter was sent by the chief rabbi of Alexandria to Mosheh Hayim Naim.
    - Letter of thanks to a donor from the Alexandrian rabbis, Avraham Avikhzer and [Refael Miprezola?], Circa 1940-circa 1950; MS.1825.1227; 1 leaf; 13 x 21 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 23)
      Place: Alexandria.
    - Letter from the wife of Nisim ben Binyamin Ohana, rabbi of Port Said, to a woman friend named Berta, Circa 1930s; MS.1825.1228; 2 pages; 28 centimeters. (Box 25, Folder 23)
      Place: Port Said. Date printed on stationery is 193_.
    - Letter sent from Alexandria requesting donations for the community, 1714; MS.1825.1372; 1 leaf; 14 x 19 centimeters. Some worm damage with minimal loss of text. (Box 25, Folder 23)
- Tunisia, 1818-1946; Series XIII
  Series XIII contains legal documents, homilies, responsa and letters from Djerba (Jarbah, Ḥawmat al-Sūq) and Tunis, as well as a few items from other towns in Tunisia. The documents in the first section of this series (folders 1-11) have individual entries in the finding aid. The rest of the documents (folders 12-50) have a single entry in the finding aid for the collection of 120 documents from the archive of Rabbi Mosheh Kalfon ha-Kohen (1874-1950).
  - Collection of novellae on various halakhic matters by an unknown Tunisian rabbi, Circa 1900-circa 1950; MS.1825.0007; Approximately 160 pages; 17 centimeters. (Box 26, Folder 1)
    Place: Tunisia. Rabbinic manuscript written partly in pen and partly in pencil. On page 6 and elsewhere are lists of members of an unknown community in Tunisia. Many of these names exist only in Tunisia and not in Morocco: for example, Tiar, Maimon, Bukhbuz, Trablus, Mazuz, and Mamo. The manuscript may have been copied by two or more different scribes.
  - Two texts concerning hiring a surrogate to fulfill the commandment to study Torah, 1907 or 1905; MS.1825.0101; 4 pages (2 blank); 21 centimeters. Tears with some loss of text. (Box 26, Folder 2)
    Place: Djerba. One text is sent by Khalfon Kohen to Zaḳen Mosheh Mag'uz in Djerba. Since he works and does not have time to study, he asks whether he would be permitted to hire someone to study in his place and for his merit. Another anonymous rabbi gives the opinion that this is not a simple idea.
  - Letter concerning Jewish dietary law, 1900; MS.1825.0102; 4 pages; 21 centimeters. Minimal loss of text. (Box 26, Folder 2)
    Place: Djerba. A long letter concerning Jewish dietary law sent by Khalfon Kohen to Zaḳen Mosheh Mag'uz. The letter contains a long halakhic discussion about Jewish dietary law. Undoubtedly the writer wanted to find out whether his opinions are accepted by Mag'uz.
  - Letter concerning a halakhic problem of slaughtering, Circa 1890-circa 1910; MS.1825.0103; 4 pages (3 blank); 21 centimeters. Tears with some loss of text. (Box 26, Folder 2)
    Place: Djerba. A letter written by Khalfon Mosheh Kohen to Eliyahu Tayib concerning a halakhic problem of slaughtering. In the same document there is a second letter on the same subject. It is interesting to note that that Khalfon gives his address in Djerba in care of Shalom Kohen, Djerba.
  - Legal decision concerning leaven on Passover, 1944?; MS.1825.0104; 2 pages; 21 centimeters. (Box 26, Folder 2)